William E. Fredeman Collection of William Bell Scott, the Scott Family, and Alice Boyd, 1820-1899.: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Series 1: William Bell Scott Family Papers, 1830-1890; 1733-1893; 5 boxes
  - Scott, William Bell, 1830-1893; 5 boxes (1 partial)
    - Personal Documents, circa 1854-1890; 2 boxes (1 partial)
      - Address Book, circa 1870-1890; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 17)
        Contains over 100 holograph entries with addresses for William Bell Scott's friends and acquaintances, including many central Pre-Raphaelite artists, writers, and associated figures, including William Morris, John Everett Millais, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, Christina Rossetti, and William Michael Rossetti. Also includes notes about travel accommodations and Scott's models.
      - Calling Cards, circa 1870-1890; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 18)
        Includes several copies of William Bell Scott's calling card, listing his residence as Belle Vue House at 92 Cheyne Walk in London, and one that Scott kept from Alice Boyd at Penkill Castle.
      - Passport, 1854-1862; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Personal Document Box, circa 1860s-1890; 1 item (Box 6)
        This cedar and metal document box with "WBS" inscribed on lid, contained many of William Bell Scott's most personal documents, including his passport, address books, and other items. Included inside is a key for Scott's large metal strong box, which contained various personal and family papers.
      - Prints Sold Record Books, 1870-1884; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 52)
        Two booklets of records of prints sold by William Bell Scott, including one containing information on prints sold from 1870 to 1878 and the sale of Scott's private collection to Ellis in 1882 and one documenting the sale of prints in 1884.
      - Signature Used for Printing and Calling Cards, undated; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Stamps Bearing Dante Gabriel Rossetti's Monogram, "DGR", circa 1870-1882; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Scott, George, 1733-1754; 3.0 folders
    Documents are arranged chronologically.
    George Scott, skinner and burgess of Lanark, was the great-grandfather of William Bell Scott. This file group contains documents related to feudal property rights to a family home at Bloomgate and his marriage to Jean Hunter, as well as a guild ticket.
    - Contract of Marriage between George Scott and Jean Hunter, 1733 December 6-1739; Signed holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Discharge of Jean Hunter to George Scott, Her Husband, 1734; Signed holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Instrument of Sasine (Delivery of Feudal Property) from Lanark, 1739 September 21; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Burgess and Guildry Ticket Allowing George Scott (a Skinner by Trade) Liberties and Privileges for Lanark of Glasgow, 1754 May 24; Illuminated holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Scott, Robert (the Elder), 1765-1768; 3 folders
    Robert Scott (the elder) was the grandfather of William Bell Scott, a skinner and tax collector who lived at Bloomgate in Lanark and later in Musselburgh. This file group contains documents regarding feudal property and his marriage to Grizell Meikle.
    - Discharge Assignation and Nomination by Grizell Meikle to Robert Scott, 1765; Signed holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Contract of Marriage between Robert Scott and Grizell Meikle, 1768; Signed holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Instrument of Sasine (Delivery of Feudal Property) Produced by William Brown, 1768; Holograph document on vellum 1 item (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Scott, Robert (the Younger), 1806-1847; 8 folders
    Papers are arranged chronologically, with undated sketches at the end.
    Robert Scott (1777-1841), the father of William Bell Scott, was an engraver of small book illustrations and landscapes, active in Lanark and Edinburgh, Scotland. This file group contains legal documents regarding feudal property rights and guild membership, a letter, and two drawings, as well as estate papers retained by David Scott after his father's death. In 1800, Robert Scott married Ross Bell, the mother of David Scott and William Bell Scott.
    - Edinburgh Burgess Ticket for Robert Scott (Engraver), 1806 July 5; Printed document on vellum 1 item (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Erskine, David (11th Earl of Buchan), to Robert Scott, 1814 October 2; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Instrument of Sasine (Delivery of Feudal Property) in Favor of Robert Scott and Ross Bell, His Spouse, 1822 July 23; Holograph document on vellum 1 item (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Codicil to Disposition and Settlement by Robert Scott, 1841-1846; Holograph copy 1 item (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Act of Property by the Manager of the Kirk and Kirk Yard of Canongate in Favor of David Scott's Request for a Gravesite for Robert Scott, 1844 July 18-November 20; Holograph document and 2 holograph receipts 1 item (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Includes two receipts.
    - Account Current Between J & J Macandrew and the Trustees of the Late Mr. Robert Scott, 1847 May 19; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Scott, Robert, "Epicureans", undated; Pen and ink drawing 1 item (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Signed, "R.S."
    - Scott, Robert, "Bookishly Inclined", undated; Pen and ink drawing 1 item (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Scott, David, 1833-1852; 15 folders
    Papers are arranged chronologically.
    David Scott (1806-1849), a Scottish historical painter, was the older brother of William Bell Scott. This file group includes correspondence, an essay manuscript, and estate papers kept by William Bell Scott, who inherited his brother's property upon his death, as well as compiled his memoirs.
    Of note are two lengthy holograph letters from David Scott to his father describing his experiences while studying painting in Rome in 1833 and 1834. An additional letter, from David Scott to William Bell Scott describing his philosophy and practice of art, can be found with William Bell Scott's personal correspondence.
    - Scott, David, to Robert Scott, 1833 February 23; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Written from Rome.
    - Scott, David, to Robert Scott, 1834 February 4; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Written from Rome, describing David Scott's art studies abroad.
    - Scottish Etching Club, to David Scott, 1842 May 9-12; AL 1 item (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Contains a document listing the club's "Resolutions Proposed for Adoption."
    - Unidentified "Inhabitant of Dundee," to David Scott, 1843 July 16; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Letter regards David Scott's painting Vasco de Gama Passing the Cape of Good Hope.
    - Scott, David, "Of the Paintings and Mosaics of Pompeii and Herculaneum" Essay Draft, circa 1845; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Last Will and Testament of David Scott, 1846 June 12; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Also contains added annotations and inscriptions by others.
    - Testament of David Scott, Giving William Bell Scott Sole Ownership of all his Property, 1846 June 12-1849 March 12; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Receipt Attesting to William Bell Scott's Payment for John Sterling's Release of Rights to David Scott's Painting Vasco de Gama Passing the Cape of Good Hope, 1849 March 20; ALS 1 item (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Appraisement of the Effects which Belonged to the Deceased David Scott, Earl Daly House, Edinburgh, 1849 March 21; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Auction Roll Belonging to Mrs. Scott for Items Sold at Earl Daly House, Enumerating Auction of Items from Estate, 1849 May 9; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - William Bell Scott Account with Edinburgh Booksellers C.B. Tait and Thomas Nisbet for Pictures and Sketches of David Scott, 1851 March 1; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Official Testament Dative and Inventory of Debts and Sums of Money Owed to David Scott, 1852 August 5; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Document shows an amount totaling 1384 British sterling to William Bell Scott.
    - Stamped Receipt of Debt Paid by William Bell Scott for Debt Due from David Scott's Estate, 1852 September 15; 1 item (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Residuary Account of Mr. David Scott, 1852; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 50)
      Document shows debt totaling 809 British sterling.
    - Statement of Amount of Money Realized from the Sale of David Scott's Pictures, Books, and Effects, 1852; Holograph document 1 item (Box 3, Folder 51)
      Document shows amount totaling 818 British sterling.
- Series 2: Alice Boyd Family Papers, 1843-1897; 23 folders
  Alice Boyd's correspondence is followed by family correspondence, arranged alphabetically by sender, with other documents and manuscripts at the end.
  This series includes materials related to William Bell Scott's companion, Alice Boyd, and her family, primarily personal and family correspondence related to the Boyd, Courtney, and Losh families, along with one estate document. Alice Boyd owned Penkill Castle in Ayrshire, where William Bell Scott, among other known Pre-Raphaelite artists and associates, resided while working on various creative projects. Present is Boyd's correspondence with some of these figures regarding their visits to the castle, as well as her correspondence with publishers and other parties regarding Scott's work after his death. Family correspondence pertains mainly to the family's alkali business and the status of Penkill Castle, and also includes W.J. Linton's condolences to the heirs of Alice Boyd following her death in 1897. One family document is also present, regarding the disposition of the property of William Losh, Boyd's grandfather, following the sale of his alkali works business, as well as an unsigned manuscript by an unknown relative of Alice Boyd from the late 1890s, titled "The History of an Old Ayrshire Mansion," which documents the life of Alice Boyd and several major Pre-Raphaelites at Penkill Castle.
  Items of note include a letter from Christina Rossetti to Alice Boyd, following a visit to the castle in the late 1860s, as well as a letter from Spencer Boyd, Alice's brother, describing his visit to Penkill Castle prior to their residence.
  - Boyd, Alice, circa 1868-1895; 17 folders
    Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with unidentified items at the end.
    This file group includes Alice Boyd's personal correspondence with notable friends and associates, including William Bell Scott, Christina Rossetti, W.J. Linton, and Frederick Burton.
    - Aitken, Mary Carlisle, to Alice Boyd, undated; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Boyd, Evelyn M. Courtney, to Alice Boyd, 1869 February 2; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Regarding finances, the Courtney family crest, and Penkill Castle.
    - Boyd, Spencer, to Alice Boyd, circa 1855-1857; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Describing an early visit to Penkill Castle by Spencer Boyd, the brother of Alice Boyd, prior to their residence.
    - Burton, Frederick W., to Alice Boyd, 1877 March 15-16; 2 ALSs 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Combes, W. (Editor of Illustrated London News) to Alice Boyd, 1890 November 27-December 16; 4 ALSs 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Elkin Mathews and John Lane Publishers, to Alice Boyd, 1895 February 18; TLS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Regarding Alice Boyd's request for the return of the wood blocks and manuscript for A Poet's Harvest Home.
    - Ellis, F.S., to Alice Boyd, 1870 April 16-May 25; 4 ALSs 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Kennedy, Thomas F., to Alice Boyd, 1878 September 2-1879 February 12; 7 ALSs 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Linton, William J., to Alice Boyd, 1891 May 1-1896 August 17; 8 ALSs 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Losh, James, to Alice Boyd, 1877 November 22; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - MacLimont, John, to Alice Boyd, 1875 April 19; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Contains printed advertisement on "Growing Wood."
    - Rossetti, Christina, to Alice Boyd, circa 1868-1870; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Letter regards a recent visit by Rossetti to Penkill Castle.
    - Scott, William Bell, to Alice Boyd, 1879 May 29-June 10; 3 ALSs and a watercolor valentine 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Taylor, John (Art Association), to Alice Boyd, 1878 September 20; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Throun, David, to Alice Boyd, 1879 March 24-August 20; 2 ALSs 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified Artist, to Alice Boyd, undated; AL 1 item (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Letter mentions a trip to the National Gallery.
    - Unidentified Person, from Alice Boyd, undated; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Letter mentions the Burne-Jones Family.
  - Courtney, Henry, to Unidentified Person, undated; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Text is crossed out.
  - Dobson, William Charles, to Seth Barrett, 1843 November 28; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Linton, W.J., to Evelyn M. Courtney-Boyd, 1897 April 26-September 20; 2 ALSs and 3 envelopes 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 20)
    These letters, written on mourning stationary, were sent after the death of Alice Boyd.
  - MacDonald, D., to William Losh, 1843 December 26; ALS 1 item (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Soliciting information about alkali manufacturing.
  - Mayhew, Margaret Boyd, to William Losh, circa 1855 August 24; ALS and 3 pencil sketches 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Includes 3 pencil sketches of Penkill Castle.
  - Estate Document Regarding William Losh, 1874 May-1887 August 22; Signed holograph document 1 item (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "The History of an Old Ayrshire Mansion", circa 1894-1899; Unsigned manuscript 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Twelve-page manuscript by an unknown relative of Alice Boyd, possibly Margaret Courtney-Boyd or another of Boyd's nieces, which includes a detailed report on the history and inhabitants of Penkill Castle during the time of Alice Boyd's residence, with special attention to the activities of several major Pre-Raphaelites, including William Bell Scott, Dante Gabriel Rossetti, Christina Rossetti, Arthur Hughes, and others.
- Series 3: Related Materials, 1834-1890s; 8 folders
  Poems are arranged alphabetically by title, followed by a letter fragment and clippings.
  This series includes related papers and clippings that were retained with the collection from Penkill Castle. Included are several holograph poems by others, some copied out in the hand of William Bell Scott and others by an unknown party. Also present are a letter fragment, and clippings of Scott's early work in print magazines.
  - "Barton Church" (1673) Poem by Unknown Poet, undated; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 24)
    In the hand of William Bell Scott.
  - "Beatrice," Poem by Arthur Joseph Munby, 1890 May; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Written for the Beatrice Festival at Florence.
  - "For who the melodies of morn can tell..." Minstrel Poem Fragment, undated; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - "Lines in the Epitaph on the tomb of Shakespeare's favorite daughter," from Margaret Stokes, April 16, no year; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "The New Forest," Poem by Unknown Poet, 1896; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Includes two Boyd family heraldry engravings.
  - "Sonnet on Niccolo dell' Abate" (1590) by Agostino Carracci, undated; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Letter Fragment, Signed "William Dyer", undated; 1 item (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 1834-1844; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Contains clippings of William Bell Scott's early writings and engravings, including "The Martyr and the Pilgrim," a poem he published in Tait's Magazine in August, 1834, and his engravings published in Cleave's London Satirist and Gazette of Variety in the late 1830s or early 1840s.